<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-16T15:18:34+09:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Adrian Kosasih</title><subtitle>Adrian&apos;s homepage </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Strange Spinach</title><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-strange-spinach/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Strange Spinach"/><published>2025-02-16T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-16T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-strange-spinach</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-strange-spinach/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/spinach1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/spinach1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/spinach1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/spinach1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The strange spinach </div> <p>Last month, my wife brought home a very unusual spinach. It was shorter and wider than the typical spinach you find in Japan. The label read <strong>寒じめちぢみほうれん草</strong>(kanjime chijimi hourensou), which roughly translates to <em>cold-shrunk</em> spinach. A quick Google search led me to an unexpected realization: the spinach I grew up eating as a kid wasn’t actually <em>true</em> spinach.</p> <h3 id="the-curious-case-of-shrunk-spinach">The Curious Case of Shrunk Spinach</h3> <p>Let’s start with this unique variety. It’s naturally shorter, which explains its compact shape, but what makes it special is how it’s grown. Cultivated in cold winter climates, it develops a higher sugar content, making it sweeter than regular spinach [^1]. However, I couldn’t find a clear explanation of whether the cold also contributes to its shrinkage.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/spinach2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/spinach2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/spinach2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/spinach2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The back side </div> <p>And the taste? Sweeter, but also more bitter than typical spinach. The texture was crispier, which I really enjoyed.</p> <h3 id="my-spinach-revelation">My Spinach Revelation</h3> <p>Now, onto my realization. The “spinach” I ate as a kid in Indonesia wasn’t actually <em>spinacia oleracea</em>, the species commonly known as spinach in Japan and many other parts of the world. Instead, <strong>bayam</strong> (what we call spinach in Indonesia) belongs to the <strong>Amaranthus</strong> family (e.g., <em>Amaranthus dubius</em>) [^2].</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4d/Amaranthus_palmeri-480.webp 480w,https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4d/Amaranthus_palmeri-800.webp 800w,https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4d/Amaranthus_palmeri-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4d/Amaranthus_palmeri.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The "spinach" in Indonesia. Image by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Pompilid">Pompilid</a>, licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>. </div> <p>I had never really thought about it before. I did notice that Japanese spinach had much larger leaves than what I grew up with, but I assumed it was just a difference in quality. It turns out, they’re entirely different plants!</p> <p>Taste-wise, from what I remember, Amaranthus spinach and Spinacia spinach aren’t all that different.</p> <p>Well, you learn something new every day.</p> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <p>[^1] <strong>コープさっぽろの広報誌 Cho-co-tto（ちょこっと）</strong>, “冬限定の『ちぢみほうれん草』、普通のほうれん草と何が違うの？,” <em>Note</em>, Jan. 5, 2021. [Online]. Available: <a href="https://note.com/chocotto_coop/n/n771255dba316">https://note.com/chocotto_coop/n/n771255dba316</a> [Accessed: Feb. 15, 2025].</p> <p>[^2] <strong>“Amaranth,”</strong> <em>Wikipedia</em>, n.d. [Online]. Available: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amaranth">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amaranth</a>. [Accessed: Feb. 15, 2025].</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian</name></author><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last month, my wife brought home a very unusual spinach. It was shorter and wider than the typical spinach you find in Japan. A quick Google search led me to an unexpected realization of my childhood.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My review of Why We Sleep: The New Science of Sleep and Dreams</title><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/book-review-why-we-sleep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My review of Why We Sleep: The New Science of Sleep and Dreams"/><published>2025-02-11T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/book-review-why-we-sleep</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/book-review-why-we-sleep/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/book_why_we_sleep-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/book_why_we_sleep-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/book_why_we_sleep-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/book_why_we_sleep.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Why We Sleep by Matthew Walker </div> <h3 id="now-i-need-to-sleep">Now I need to sleep</h3> <p>This blog won’t be long; I tried to find the motivation to write a longer post, but sleep won that battle. Ironically, skipping a blog post didn’t improve my sleep quality. (Just kidding… or am I?)</p> <p><strong>Why We Sleep</strong> begins by defining sleep and explaining how it works. It covers sleep stages, REM (Rapid Eye Movement) sleep, and NREM (Non-Rapid Eye Movement) sleep. While informative, the biology-heavy section nearly put me to sleep (which, I guess, is proof that the book works?).</p> <p>The most eye-opening (or should I say eye-closing?) part was the section on sleep deprivation. Some of the consequences are shockingly severe—lack of sleep can literally kill you. Walker backs up his claims with studies on how sleep affects our health, which I found compelling.</p> <p>That said, I came across reviews mentioning that some of his claims are disputed by experts. Still, from my own bodily experience, I agree with most of his points. I’ve definitely felt the effects of sleep deprivation firsthand from my all-nighters. So, I’m going to try following some of his advice for better sleep:</p> <ul> <li>No coffee after 2 PM</li> <li>No heavy meals before bed</li> <li>No intense exercise right before sleep</li> <li>Prepping the bedroom for optimal sleep</li> </ul> <p>And with that… time to sleep!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian</name></author><category term="book"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This book practically told me to sleep — and honestly, it was right. I should've slept more.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My review of Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World</title><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/book-review-deep-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My review of Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World"/><published>2025-01-22T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/book-review-deep-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/book-review-deep-work/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/book_deep_work-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/book_deep_work-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/book_deep_work-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/book_deep_work.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World by Cal Newport on my Kindle </div> <h3 id="lost-time">Lost Time</h3> <p>Until recently, I was (am still) overwhelmed by social media, such as Instagram and Facebook. My already limited free time at night after full-time work during the day was gone to oblivion, just to read and watch useless information.</p> <p>I felt like my life was on autopilot. Suddenly, I realized some months had passed last year. Last year was probably my busiest year due to my wedding, but still, after that, everything else felt quick.</p> <p>After I read Cal Newport’s book Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World, I understood what was (maybe) happening to me. I spent too much time on shallow tasks, like browsing social media and using my smartphone, instead of doing deep work, which requires long uninterrupted concentration.</p> <p>For some weeks before I read this book, my average screen time was around six hours/day. <em>That’s equal to my whole evening after work!</em> For comparison, my wife’s average screen time was around one to two hours/day.</p> <p>Like the saying, “The phone is smart the person isn’t.” I know I must change this.</p> <h3 id="embracing-boredom">Embracing Boredom</h3> <p>After reading this book, I applied some of his advice, such as not using social media or time-blocking. One thing among the others is “embrace boredom.” As I understand it, try letting your mind get bored without seeking entertainment. In my case, I basically try not to open my smartphone when bored (like when waiting). <em>Well, it is hard.</em></p> <p>The first few days were fine, but recently, I started going back to my old habit of looking at my phone. It seems I need to train my mind to do this.</p> <p>I remember a deep work occasion during the <em>Pelatnas</em> (Indonesian term, <em>“Pelatihan Nasional”</em>, meaning “National Training”) for International Olympiad of Astronomy and Astrophysics during my highschool days. I fondly remember there being no smartphone at that time. We were able to work long hours just to study college-level astronomy and astrophysics classes from the top university professors of the subjects in Indonesia (or maybe in SEA). Honestly, I want to return to that level of focus.</p> <p>Back to the book, I really liked Deep Work. Cal Newport successfully reminded me of the critical things I was missing by forfeiting my time to shallow entertainment. I recommend giving this book a read if you feel the same way, if you feel your time is lost to the internet.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian</name></author><category term="book"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Until recently, I was overwhelmed by social media. Reading this book made me realize how to return the time I lost to the internet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World v3.0</title><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-new-personal-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World v3.0"/><published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-new-personal-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-new-personal-website/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="hello">Hello!</h3> <p>Hi, welcome to my new website!</p> <h3 id="the-motivation-many-years-ago">The Motivation Many Years Ago</h3> <p>I have long wanted to create my own website to express my thoughts in a longer form. I actually already created one back when I worked in my previous company (Hitachi Zosen; now called Kanadevia).</p> <p>At the time, I wanted to try having my website to start writing and build a brand for myself. However, due to my lack of motivation and bad website framework, I decided to scrap that old one (there is no blog post anyway) and create a new one with GitHub Pages.</p> <h3 id="first-iteration-v10">First Iteration V1.0</h3> <p>To be honest, I just wanted a free and simple personal website. I don’t need any fancy features, as long as I can write my post and it is neat.</p> <p>I first wanted to create my website while reading about note-taking. I read many random websites and Reddit posts until I stumbled upon <a href="https://ratfactor.com/">Ratfactor</a> by Dave Gauer. I was fascinated, firstly, by his simple yet great notebook system and, secondly, by his lightweight website.</p> <p>My first website iteration was using Google Sites. It was very clean, indeed. However, I didn’t like how I had to update the website to post my blog posts manually. (Maybe it was just because I didn’t bother to search for an efficient way to do it)</p> <h3 id="second-iteration-v20">Second Iteration V2.0</h3> <p>For my second website iteration, I actually got the idea two years ago after seeing my friend Jafar’s personal website (<a href="https://ajarifi.github.io/">here</a>). His website was also pretty neat, and then I noticed the URL, GitHub.</p> <p>I then searched about it and found out about <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a>. I like the customizable theme (with many templates) and the very simple blog post organization. Basically, to add a new blog post, just push a Git commit with the blog post formatted in Markdown in the posts folder, which I am familiar with. (I still can’t say I am good with Git and Markdown, though.)</p> <p>Then, when I found out that GitHub Pages is free and can use custom URLs, it was a no-brainer to choose it.</p> <h3 id="third-iteration-v30">Third Iteration V3.0</h3> <p>Fast-forward two years, and I haven’t made any blog posts on the second website. It turned out I was too lazy and unmotivated.</p> <p>This year, I thought to myself, I would like to make my ambitions a reality. For the last few years, I have been on and off in autopilot mode. While in recent years I felt much more in control, I felt I hadn’t done anything very productive beyond my work.</p> <p>Finally, after almost two years of delay, I launched my third iteration of my website (this one) and posted a fitting first blog post today!</p> <p>I hope this is not yet another futile attempt. Let’s see how this unfolds.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian</name></author><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the first blog post for my second try to building a personal website.]]></summary></entry></feed>