<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-19T02:45:47+00:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Adrian Kosasih</title><subtitle>Adrian&apos;s homepage </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hello World v3.0</title><link href="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-new-personal-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World v3.0"/><published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-new-personal-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.adriankosasih.com/blog/2025/a-new-personal-website/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="hello">Hello!</h3> <p>Hi, welcome to my new website!</p> <h3 id="the-motivation-many-years-ago">The Motivation Many Years Ago</h3> <p>I have long wanted to create my own website to express my thoughts in a longer form. I actually already created one back when I worked in my previous company (Hitachi Zosen; now called Kanadevia).</p> <p>At the time, I wanted to try having my website to start writing and build a brand for myself. However, due to my lack of motivation and bad website framework, I decided to scrap that old one (there is no blog post anyway) and create a new one with GitHub Pages.</p> <h3 id="first-iteration-v10">First Iteration V1.0</h3> <p>To be honest, I just wanted a free and simple personal website. I don’t need any fancy features, as long as I can write my post and it is neat.</p> <p>I first wanted to create my website while reading about note-taking. I read many random websites and Reddit posts until I stumbled upon <a href="https://ratfactor.com/">Ratfactor</a> by Dave Gauer. I was fascinated, firstly, by his simple yet great notebook system and, secondly, by his lightweight website.</p> <p>My first website iteration was using Google Sites. It was very clean, indeed. However, I didn’t like how I had to update the website to post my blog posts manually. (Maybe it was just because I didn’t bother to search for an efficient way to do it)</p> <h3 id="second-iteration-v20">Second Iteration V2.0</h3> <p>For my second website iteration, I actually got the idea two years ago after seeing my friend Jafar’s personal website (<a href="https://ajarifi.github.io/">here</a>). His website was also pretty neat, and then I noticed the URL, GitHub.</p> <p>I then searched about it and found out about <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a>. I like the customizable theme (with many templates) and the very simple blog post organization. Basically, to add a new blog post, just push a Git commit with the blog post formatted in Markdown in the posts folder, which I am familiar with. (I still can’t say I am good with Git and Markdown, though.)</p> <p>Then, when I found out that GitHub Pages is free and can use custom URLs, it was a no-brainer to choose it.</p> <h3 id="third-iteration-v30">Third Iteration V3.0</h3> <p>Fast-forward two years, and I haven’t made any blog posts on the second website. It turned out I was too lazy and unmotivated.</p> <p>This year, I thought to myself, I would like to make my ambitions a reality. For the last few years, I have been on and off in autopilot mode. While in recent years I felt much more in control, I felt I hadn’t done anything very productive beyond my work.</p> <p>Finally, after almost two years of delay, I launched my third iteration of my website (this one) and posted a fitting first blog post today!</p> <p>I hope this is not yet another futile attempt. Let’s see how this unfolds.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian</name></author><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the first blog post for my second try to building a personal website.]]></summary></entry></feed>